<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../xsltforms/xsl/xsltforms.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xsltforms-options domengine="name=Fleur;url=../../xsltforms/js/fleur.js;uri=http://www.agencexml.com/Fleur;version=1.0"?>
<?xsltforms-options debug="no"?>
<?css-conversion no?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:cwb="http://bibfram.es/cwb/"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
    xmlns:ev="http://www.w3.org/2001/xml-events"
    xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/"
    xmlns:marc="http://www.loc.gov/MARC21/slim"
    xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#"
    xmlns:xf="http://www.w3.org/2002/xforms"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <head>
        <title>IVMOOC16 CoBRA Group 2 Project Website</title>
        <!-- Latest compiled and minified CSS -->
        <link rel="stylesheet"
            href="https://maxcdn.bootstrapcdn.com/bootstrap/3.3.6/css/bootstrap.min.css" />
        <!-- Optional theme -->
        <link rel="stylesheet"
            href="https://maxcdn.bootstrapcdn.com/bootstrap/3.3.6/css/bootstrap-theme.min.css" />
        <style type="text/css">
            <![CDATA[
            #wrapper{
                width:80%;
                min-height:1000px;
                margin-top:1%;
                margin-right:auto;
                margin-left:auto;
                margin-bottom:2%;
                background-color:#C0C0C0;
            }
            #title{
                text-align:center;
            }
            .xforms-label{
            
            }
            .checkbox{
                list-style-type:none;
            }
            #group-people{
            
            }
            #group-tasks{
            
            }
            #authorship{
                width:100%;
                margin-right:auto;
                margin-left:auto;
                text-align:center;
            }
            .authors{
                margin-top:1%;
                width:20%;
                float:left;
            }
            hr{
                color:white;
                width:100%;
                float:left;
            }
            #sketches{
                width:100%;
                margin-left:auto;
                margin-right:auto;
            
            
            }
            #choro{
                margin:0 2% 0 0;
                width:600px;
                float:left;
            
            }
            #network{
                margin:0 2% 0 0;
                width:600px;
                float:left;
            
            
            }
            #related-work{
                width:100%;
                float:left;
            }
            #stats{
                width:100%;
                float:left;
            }
            #viz{
                width:100%;
                float:left;
            }
            #insights{
                width:100%;
                float:left;
            }
            #if{
                width:60%;
                height:auto;
            }
            #ls{
                width:60%;
                height:auto;
            }
            #li{
                width:60%;
                height:auto;
            }
            #sg{
                width:100%;
                height:auto;
            }
            #f2m{
                width:100%;
                height:auto;
            }
            #gephi2{
                width:100%;
                height:auto;
                background:black;
            }
            #citations{
                width:100%;
                float:left;
            }
            .bold{
                font-weight:bold;
            }
            .ital{
                font-style:italic;
            }
            #validation{
                width:100%;
                float:left;
            }
            #challenges{
                width:100%;
                float:left;
            }]]>
        </style>
        <xf:model id="default-model">
            <xf:instance id="default-instance" src="data/data.xml"
            ></xf:instance>
        </xf:model>
    </head>
    <body>
        <div id="wrapper" class="container">
            <div id="title">
                <h1>Comic Book Readership Archive (CoBRA)</h1>
                <h2>Exploring Comic Book Fan Mail across Gender and
                    Geography</h2>
            </div>
            <xf:group ref="/data">
                <xf:group id="authorship">
                    <xf:repeat nodeset="group/people/person">
                        <div class="authors">
                            <a href="{@canvas}">
                                <xf:output value="name"/>
                            </a>
                            <div>Indiana University</div>
                            <xf:output value="@mail"/>
                        </div>
                    </xf:repeat>
                </xf:group>
                <hr />
                <xf:group id="work-in-progress">
                    <h3>Link to current <a href="/resources/fans/530/"
                        target="_blank"
                            >work-in-progress</a>.</h3>
                    <p class="ital">This page represents one of the letter-writers from the
                        dataset and is an example of an attempt to use linked
                        data to visualize some of the relationships present in
                        the data. In a final version, the page will contain
                        active links to pages representing other entities
                        in the CoBRA universe (places, comics, fans).</p>
                </xf:group>
                <xf:group id="scope">
                    <h3>Project scope and significance</h3>
                    <p>The project will produce a thematic visualization of
                        published fan mail (taken from the time slice provided,
                        1961-1973) and consisting of several subcomponents that
                        address the relevant themes in the dataset:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Geographic origin</li>
                        <li>Gender representation</li>
                        <li>Comic book series popularity</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>These subcomponent visualizations will provide a unified
                        view of comic book readership in the form of a world
                        geospatial representation with a count analysis of
                        letters published and a network analysis of letter
                        writers and comic book series. The discrete quantifiable
                        measures will include letter-writer breakdowns from U.S.
                        states and countries and correlations among gender,
                        location, and comic book series.</p>
                    <p>The significance of the CoBRA project lies in its
                        examination of an area of popular cultural
                        studies--comic book fan letters--that has not yet been
                        adequately research or documented. A historical database
                        of fan letters provides a unique resource for answering
                        research questions about the feedback loop between
                        production and consumption in the comic book genre.</p>
                </xf:group>
                <xf:group id="sketches">
                    <h3>Sketches/preliminary visualizations</h3>
                    <div id="choro">
                        <h4>Choropleth map of letters by U.S. state:</h4>
                        <img src="resources/letters-choro.svg"
                            alt="Choropleth map of comic book fan letters by U.S. state"
                         />
                    </div>
                    <div id="network">
                        <h4>Sample network visualization of comic book series
                            and letter writers:</h4>
                        <img src="resources/cobra-network.svg"
                            alt="Choropleth map of comic book fan letters by U.S. state"
                         />
                    </div>
                </xf:group>
                <xf:group id="related-work">
                    <h3>Related work</h3>
                    <p>The textbook Visual Insights<sup>1</sup> contains
                        exemplary visualizations and thematic presentations that
                        are relevant to the CoBRA dataset, including the case
                        studies "One Hundred Years of ISIS" (p. 262) and
                        Visualizing NYC Hive (p. 268). The rough outline of our
                        proposed CoBRA visualization is based on observing these
                        thematic approaches to visualization and data
                        encapsulation.</p>
                    <p>A search on some of the reference suggestions in the
                        CoBRA project description reveals a few scholarly
                        articles and materials relevant to the history of comic
                        book readership and relevant to the formation of the
                        CoBRA project. These references are useful for
                        understanding the context around the project, but not in
                        terms of auxiliary raw data or exemplary
                        visualizations.</p>
                    <p>A search on comic-book readership online produces some
                        more specific and contextually relevant data and
                        visualization examples, including breakdowns of
                        demographic-based and gender-based fan discussion and
                        readership statistics. The Internet and Internet
                        discussion and fan sites appear to be the modern
                        replacement of older fan publications, and is naturally
                        more expedient and simpler to harvest data from
                        contemporary online sites and archives than from print
                        sources. As an example, the Graphic Policy website
                        details such statistics, as harvested from
                            Facebook.<sup>2</sup> depicts pie-charts and line
                        graphs depicting comic book demographics).</p>
                    <p>Although interesting, it is not clear that online sites
                        with present-day statistics provide any significant
                        guidance to the task of characterizing, analyzing, and
                        visualizing the historical data segment presented in the
                        CoBRA project. An expanded scope that includes
                        comparison to present-day statistics might be
                        useful.</p>
                    <p>A previous version of the CoBRA dataset has been
                        visualized by Anirudh R. A., Ashish Shendure, Brittany
                        Yoder, Jae Eun Kum, and Shambhavi
                            Dhargalkar.<sup>3</sup> Our work will differ from
                        theirs by focusing more on geospatial and network
                        visualization techniques. Another exemplary
                        visualization cited by Anirudh R. A. et al., which
                        includes digital images and transcripts of comic book
                        fan letters, can be found on the hosted TimeMapper
                            website.<sup>4</sup></p>
                </xf:group>
                <xf:group id="stats">
                    <h3>Data cleaning and preprocessing</h3>
                    <h4>Gender data</h4>
                    <p>The approach to gender identification of names was based
                        on using the Social Security Tables from 1880-1914 to
                        identify registration trends. The tables were globbed
                        into a master table and sorted by occurrence based on
                        gender. The dominant count was used as the basis of
                        projection: for example, in the case of the name
                        "Billy," the ambigendrous ratio is given by:
                            <code>Billy</code><code>Male</code><code>381527</code>
                        |
                        <code>Billy</code><code>Female</code><code>5346</code>.</p>
                    <p>Based on historic registrations, "Billy" was projected to
                        be female in only 1.38% of occurrences. Therefore the
                        code was designed to project the name as male (barring
                        any obvious contraindications such as a
                            <code>person_title</code> value of "Mrs."</p>
                    <h4>Geocoding data</h4>
                    <p>Geocoding data from the Google Map web services has been
                        harvested and will be utilized in the project's next
                        phase of visualizations. Using street-level geocoding
                        from Google allows for more granular mapping and
                        visualization versus centroid-based geocoding found in
                        applications such as Tableau (also, Tableau allows for
                        custom geocoding import, so one can gain very granular
                        geocoding information and still use Tableau
                        visualizations). The particular tools used included the
                        geopy module and Python (registration with Google was
                        necessary). A further advantage of Google is the
                        byproduct of corrected, standardized addressing (i.e.,
                        address cleaning) for possible future incorporation into
                        the dataset.</p>
                    <p>In some cases preliminary cleaning of address data was
                        necessary (e.g., where the city and state were
                        recognizable but the country was left null). This
                        process preceded more granular address cleanup.</p>
                    <h3>Summary statistics</h3>
                    <p>A summary of the dataset is presented in the table below.
                        An initial count of names in the dataset yielded a total
                        of 3,168 unique names. Person data is in the process of
                        being further cleaned and reconciled, so this figure may
                        change.</p>
                    <table class="table table-striped">
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <td>Comic book series</td>
                                <td>Comic book issues</td>
                                <td>Fan letters</td>
                                <td>Countries</td>
                                <td>Unique names of letter writers</td>
                                <td>Gender of letter writers (inferred)</td>
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td>11</td>
                                <td>610</td>
                                <td>3703</td>
                                <td>38</td>
                                <td>3237</td>
                                <td>
                                    <table class="table table-striped">
                                        <thead>
                                        <tr>
                                        <td>Male</td>
                                        <td>Female</td>
                                        <td>Null</td>
                                        </tr>
                                        </thead>
                                        <tbody>
                                        <tr>
                                        <td>2863</td>
                                        <td>266</td>
                                        <td>108</td>
                                        </tr>
                                        </tbody>
                                    </table>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </xf:group>
                <xf:group id="viz">
                    <h3>Visualizations</h3>
                    <p>Our initial approach to visualizing the CoBRA data has
                        focused on the variables of gender and geographic
                        location (currently limited to US states).
                        Methodologically, we have explored three techniques:
                        statistical visualization, geospatial visualization, and
                        network visualization.</p>
                    <h4><span class="bold">Statistical</span></h4>
                    <p>To analyze the fan letter data, a Pivot Table was created
                        in Excel of all of the CoBRA data. For rows, the
                            <code>series_name</code> and <code>issue_id</code>
                        data fields were selected. For the value field, the
                        count of <code>issue_id</code> was selected. This
                        provided a count of fan letters for each individual
                        issue and also provided an overall count of fan letters
                        for each series.</p>
                    <p>To create a frequency distribution of fan letters and
                        issues, columns were numbered from the lowest value of
                        fan letters per issue (1) to the highest value (71). A
                        binary <code>=if()</code> statement matrix was created,
                        referencing the values in the pivot tables to those of
                        the numbered columns. If the number of fan letters was
                        equal to the column number, the cell would show 1. If it
                        did not, the cell would show 0. The columns were then
                        totaled to obtain the number of individual issues
                        receiving each number of fan letters. Once these values
                        were obtained, a scatterplot was created with the x-axis
                        representing the number of fan letters and the y-axis
                        representing the number of issues.</p>
                    <p>Referencing the same pivot table, a histogram of the
                        total number of fan letters for each comic book series
                        was created, as well as one for the average number of
                        fan letters per issue in each series.</p>
                    <p>An additional histogram was created to represent the
                        breakdown of gender by state.</p>
                    <hr />
                    <h4>Links to preliminary statistical visualizations</h4>
                    <hr />
                    <h5><a href="resources/issue-freq.png"><span class="bold"
                                >Frequency distribution of fan letters and
                                issues</span></a></h5>
                    <hr />
                    <h5><a href="resources/letters-series.png"><span
                                class="bold">Total fan letters by
                            series</span></a></h5>
                    <hr />
                    <h5><a href="resources/letters-issue.png"><span class="bold"
                                >Average number of fan letters per issue,
                                grouped by series</span></a></h5>
                    <hr />
                    <h5><a href="resources/state-gender.png"><span class="bold"
                                >Bar graph of gender totals by
                        state</span></a></h5>
                    <hr />
                    <h4><span class="bold">Geospatial</span>: choropleth map of
                        the proporation of female-to-male letter writers by US
                        state</h4>
                    <p>To visualize the female-to-male proportion of CoBRA
                        letter writers, R was utilized to analyze, clean, and
                        reshape data.<sup>5</sup> From there, shape files from
                        ArcGIS were used to map the female-to-male proportion of
                        US letter writers. The data was read from R and persons
                        were filtered by <code>id_person_dim</code> to identify
                        unique authors and then grouped by gender and state to
                        aggregate gender totals.</p>
                    <p>The female-to-male proportion was calculated from these
                        totals and map tools were used to map, fortify, and
                        merge state dimensions to state names from the data
                        file. This data was plotted as a Choropleth Map with
                        ggplot2. The higher the proportion of female-to-male
                        values, the darker the shade of red.</p>
                    <hr />
                    <h4>Link to preliminary geospatial visualization</h4>
                    <h5><a href="resources/f2m.png"><span class="bold"
                                >Choropleth map showing the proportion of
                                female-to-male letter writers by
                            state</span></a></h5>
                    <hr />
                    <h4><span class="bold">Network</span>: force-directed graph
                        of comic book series and letter writers, color-coded by
                        gender</h4>
                    <p>To visualize the connections among letter writers and
                        comic book series, a force-directed network graph was
                        encoded as a GraphML/XML file and rendered in Gephi. The
                        BaseX XML database and XQuery interpreter was used to
                        convert the CoBRA CSV data file into an internal XML
                        representation. An XQuery script was then written to
                        produce node and edge lists using GraphML notation. Node
                        values were color-coded to distinguish between series
                        nodes and letter-writer nodes, the latter of which were
                        color-coded by gender (male, female, null).</p>
                    <p>The resulting GraphML file contained a total of 3248
                        nodes and 3482 edges. Once imported into Gephi, a series
                        of network statistics was calculated, including degree,
                        betweenness centrality, and modularity class. These
                        statistics are still being explored and have not yet
                        been incorporated into additional visualizations. The
                        network was laid out using Gephi's implementation of the
                        Fruchterman Reingold force-directed layout, with the
                        following parameters:</p>
                    <table class="table table-striped">
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <td>Area</td>
                                <td>Gravity</td>
                                <td>Speed</td>
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td>10000.0</td>
                                <td>7.0</td>
                                <td>10.0</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <p>Nodes were then sized by degree, on a scale of 8 to 50,
                        and proportionally sized node labels were added. Labels
                        were then filtered to show only those labels whose nodes
                        had a degree greater than 9.</p>
                    <hr />
                    <h4>Link to preliminary network visualization</h4>
                    <h5><a href="resources/gephi.xml"><span class="bold"
                                >Force-directed network graph of comic book
                                series with nodes color-coded by
                            gender</span></a></h5>
                    <hr />
                </xf:group>
                <xf:group id="insights">
                    <h3>Insights</h3>
                    <p>The preliminary phase of visualization and analysis has
                        revealed some basic insights regarding the contours of
                        the data:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li><span class="ital">Fantastic Four</span> (901
                            issues) and <span class="ital">The Amazing
                                Spider-Man</span> (1092 issues) represented the
                            greatest portion of the data by series, but <span
                                class="ital">The Avengers</span> and <span
                                class="ital">The X-Men</span> had the highest
                            average of number of letters per issue (8.28 and
                            7.69 letters per issue, respectively).</li>
                        <li>All 50 fifty US states and several other countries
                            were represented in the data; California and New
                            York were by far the biggest contributors.</li>
                        <li>The letter writers in the dataset were
                            overwhelmingly male, but the most active letter
                            writer (Shirley Gorman, with 17 letters) was
                            female.</li>
                        <li>Alaska, New Hampshire, Idaho, Arizona, and New
                            Mexico were the only states with a proportion of
                            female-to-male letter writers greater than 25%
                            (1:4).</li>
                        <li>By region, the Pacific Northwest had the highest
                            proportion of female-to-male letter writers.</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>The next phase of visualization and analysis should yield
                        additional insights into the connections among the
                        people, places, and comic books represented in the
                        dataset.</p>
                </xf:group>
                <xf:group id="validation">
                    <h3>Validation and redesign</h3>
                    <h4>Deduplication</h4>
                    <p>During the data clean-up process, many records were
                        observed to have duplicate names but different
                            <code>id_person_dim</code> identifiers and different
                        location information. Given the selective nature of the
                        data, it is still very possible that these are the same
                        individuals writing from different locations. For
                        example:</p>
                    <table class="table table-striped">
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <td>id_person_dim</td>
                                <td>Name</td>
                                <td>Address</td>
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td>2902</td>
                                <td>Adams Richard</td>
                                <td>102 Bryan Ct. Apt. 101 Laurel MD US
                                    10810</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>2458</td>
                                <td>Adams Richard</td>
                                <td>Rt. #1, Box 439 Oakiland MD US 21550</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <p>In this case, the issue dates are two years apart. It's
                        reasonable to assume that Adam could have moved from
                        Laurel, Maryland, to Oakland, Maryland. The following
                        disambiguation algorithm was decided upon: if a name is
                        the same, the address is within the same state, and the
                        difference between publication dates is within 2 years,
                        then identifiers for this person will be merged.</p>
                    <p>In terms of workflow, all duplicate names were extracted
                        with their identifiers to a new file (901 records) and
                        merged according to the disambiguation algorithm.
                        Finally, the cleaned file will be used to generate more
                        visualizations whose data points are less dispersed.</p>
                    <p>Conversely, there are also data validation issues for
                        cases in which names are identical or similar, but the
                        location is the same. For example:</p>
                    <table class="table table-striped">
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <td>id_person_dim</td>
                                <td>Name</td>
                                <td>Address</td>
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td>2472</td>
                                <td>Burton Mike</td>
                                <td>1149 Greenwood St Bellefontaine OH</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>2473</td>
                                <td>Silvers Mike</td>
                                <td>1149 Greenwood St Bellefontaine OH</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>2583</td>
                                <td>Burton Mike</td>
                                <td>1149 Greenwood St Bellefontaine OH</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <h4>Geocoding</h4>
                    <p>Centroid-based geocoding was augmented with street-level
                        geocoding from Google’s geocoding web services, in order
                        to potentially produce more informative geospatial
                        visualizations. Several issues were encountered: <ol>
                            <li>street addresses not always clean enough to pass
                                through Google</li>
                            <li>street addresses that use non-standard
                                designations (e.g., "barracks" rather than
                                street)</li>
                            <li>street designations that Google silently passes
                                to a centroid based on city, state, country</li>
                        </ol>
                    </p>
                    <p>Addresses in these categories had to be flagged and
                        manually inspected or modified. More generally, it is
                        not clear that street-level geocoding adds much to the
                        visualization (does a dot on South Denver inform more
                        than a dot on centroid Denver on a small map?). At the
                        same time, there is value in clean addresses in the
                        overall dataset (the project curator might want a
                        cleaned address scheme going forward), but this is not
                        one of the deliverables asked for in the project scope. </p>
                    <h4>Gender data</h4>
                    <p>There is value, both as a learning exercise and to the
                        overall dataset, of approaching gender identification of
                        user names using a programmatic approach. The approach
                        chosen was to take the Social Security Tables from 1880
                        to 1914 and use these to identify registration trends
                        (this approach is mentioned in the client project list
                        of questions). The tables were aggregated into a master
                        table and sorted by occurrence based on gender. Issues
                        encountered included: <ol>
                            <li>ambigendrous names—names that can be either male
                                or female</li>
                            <li>names that may be present in other countries but
                                not reflected in the US SSA table
                                registrations</li>
                        </ol>
                    </p>
                    <p>In the case of ambigendrous names, a programmatic
                        mitigation is possible. The dominant count was used as
                        the basis of projection: for example, in the case of the
                        name "Billy," the ambigendrous ratio is given as: <table
                            class="table table-striped">
                            <thead>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>Name</td>
                                    <td>Gender</td>
                                    <td>Count</td>
                                </tr>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>Billy</td>
                                    <td>Male</td>
                                    <td>381527</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>Billy</td>
                                    <td>Female</td>
                                    <td>5346</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>Based on historic registrations, "Billy" was projected to
                        be female in only 1.38% of occurrences. Therefore the
                        code was designed to project the name as male (barring
                        any obvious contraindications such as a title of "Mrs."
                        There are other cases that are not as clear-cut, and in
                        which manual intervention was necessary. For example,
                        one individual had the first name "Robin" and middle
                        name given as "Christopher": in this case Robin
                        indicates female, but the addition of Christopher as a
                        middle name clearly suggests male. These cases had to be
                        flagged and mitigated manually, in lieu of additional
                        programming logic to add middle names to the gender
                        scoring process.</p>
                    <p>In the case of non-US names, these had to be mitigated
                        manually based on Google searches of name origin, usage,
                        and meaning.</p>
                    <h4>Uniqueness criteria</h4>
                    <p>One aspect of analysis that came up in the midst of
                        initial visualizations was the question of relating
                        unique versus aggregated data points for a single letter
                        writer. Many questions that one may attempt to visualize
                        have an implicit assumption of uniqueness or
                        non-uniqueness that must be addressed as part of the
                        analysis. For example, in a geospatial visualization, if
                        the same writer produces a significant number of letters
                        from a single location, should that be part of the
                        visualization or should that writer count as weight 1.
                        As an extreme consider, for example, if a single writer
                        from a town in Australia were to write 100 letters: the
                        visualization might lead one to believe that a certain
                        comic book had a significant following in Australia,
                        which would be misleading. Uniqueness and distinctness
                        are important to understand and relate.</p>
                </xf:group>
                <xf:group id="challenges">
                    <h3>Challenges and opportunities</h3>
                    <h4>Visualization design and data modeling</h4>
                    <p>One of the unique challenges of the CoBRA dataset lies in
                        finding a visualization approach that does justice to
                        the number of connections and relationships within the
                        data. The data was created using a relational database
                        schema, so many of those linkages are present, but they
                        may not be easy to highlight and visualize.</p>
                    <p>The issue of connectedness seems especially important to
                        the CoBRA data. One of the insights that has emerged
                        during the course of analysis is the importance of comic
                        books as a locus of community and connection across time
                        and space. There are several instances of multiple
                        letters from different individuals located in the same
                        place. Take the case, for example, of Ann, Valerie,
                        Wendy, Barbara, and Mary, who all wrote letters from 1
                        Sundial Lane in Birmingham, England, to the <span
                            span="ital">Fantastic Four</span> fan page in April
                        and May of 1968. There are other cases of letters that
                        appear to come from the same household, apartment
                        building, or military barracks, suggesting that comics
                        can form an "imagined community" of readers (to borrow
                        Benedict Anderson's phrase).<sup>5</sup></p>
                    <p>To address these challenges and attempt to convey a sense
                        of the complex interplay of time, space, and
                        relationships in the dataset, a different approach to
                        data modeling was adopted. A reduced version of the
                        master data table was created by removing columns that
                        contained administrative data. This core data table was
                        uploaded to the Karma data integration tool,<sup>6</sup>
                        a platform for converting relational data into linked
                        data using Semantic Web principles, vocabularies, and
                        protocols. In Karma, columns and rows were mapped to
                        linked data vocabularies such as Sean Petiya's Comic
                        Book Ontology.<sup>7</sup></p>
                    <p>The RDF linked data generated by Karma was then further
                        cleaned and converted to RDFa (RDF in Attributes) for
                        embedding into HTML Web pages.<sup>8</sup> A primary
                        component of the CoBRA Group 2 visualization deliverable
                        will focus on the ability to explore and visualize data
                        linkages through online exploration and navigation. The
                        preliminary architecture of the project website reflects
                        an attempt to implement "5-star linked data," following
                        the principles outlined by Tim Berners-Lee.<sup>9
                        </sup></p>
                    <p>An example of what this approach might look like in
                        practice is provided in <a
                            href="http://ivmooc-cobra2.github.io/resources/fans/530/"
                            >this page for Shirley A. Gorman</a>, the most
                        profilic letter-writer in the dataset.</p>
                </xf:group>
                <xf:group id="citations">
                    <h3>Citations</h3>
                    <p><sup>1 </sup>Börner, K., and D. E. Polley. 2014.
                            <i>Visual Insights</i>. Cambridge, MA: MIT
                        Press.</p>
                    <p><sup>2 </sup><a
                            href="http://graphicpolicy.com/2015/09/01/demo-graphics-comic-fandom-on-facebook-14/"
                            >http://graphicpolicy.com/2015/09/01/demo-graphics-comic-fandom-on-facebook-14/</a></p>
                    <p><sup>3 </sup><a
                            href="http://ashishshendure.com/projects/ivmooc_cobra_2015/"
                            >http://ashishshendure.com/projects/ivmooc_cobra_2015/</a></p>
                    <p><sup>4 </sup><a
                            href="http://timemapper.okfnlabs.org/anon/ik4x3a-timemapper-comics-readership-example"
                            >http://timemapper.okfnlabs.org/anon/ik4x3a-timemapper-comics-readership-example</a></p>
                    <p><sup>5 </sup>The following R packages were used: RCurl,
                        dplyr, reshape2, ggplot2, map tools, scales, and
                        RColorBrewer.</p>
                    <p><sup>5 </sup>Anderson, B. 1983. <span class="ital"
                            >Imagined Communities: Reflections on the Origin and
                            Spread of Nationalism</span>. London, England:
                        Verso.</p>
                    <p><sup>6 </sup><a href="http://usc-isi-i2.github.io/karma/"
                            >http://usc-isi-i2.github.io/karma/</a></p>
                    <p><sup>7 </sup>Petiya, S. 2015. "Comic Book Ontology." <a
                            href="https://comicmeta.org/cbo/"
                            >https://comicmeta.org/cbo/</a></p>
                    <p><sup>8 </sup><a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/rdfa-primer/"
                            >https://www.w3.org/TR/rdfa-primer/</a></p>
                    <p><sup>9 </sup><a href="http://5stardata.info/en/"
                            >http://5stardata.info/en/</a></p>
                </xf:group>
                <!-- <xf:group id="group-people" ref="group/people">
                    <h3>Group members: </h3>
                    <xf:repeat nodeset="person">
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                <a href="{name/@canvas}">
                                    <xf:output value="name"/>
                                </a>
                                <ul>
                                    <li>Roles: 
                                        <ul>
                                            <xf:repeat nodeset="roles/role">
                                                <li>
                                                    <xf:output value="."/>
                                                </li>
                                            </xf:repeat>
                                        </ul>
                                    </li>
                                </ul>
                                <ul>
                                    <li>Skills: 
                                        <ul>
                                            <xf:repeat nodeset="skills/skill">
                                                <li>
                                                    <xf:output value="."/>
                                                </li>
                                            </xf:repeat>
                                        </ul>
                                    </li>
                                </ul>
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </xf:repeat>
                </xf:group>-->
                <!--<xf:group id="group-tasks" ref="tasks">
                    <h3>Group tasks: </h3>
                    <ul>
                        <xf:repeat nodeset="task">
                            <li class="checkbox">
                                <xf:input ref="@completed">
                                    <xf:label/>
                                </xf:input>
                                <xf:output
                                    value="concat(substring(@date, 6, 2),
                                    '/',
                                    substring(@date, 9, 2),
                                    '/',
                                    substring(@date, 1, 4))"/>
                                <span>: </span>
                                <xf:group ref="@link">
                                    <a href="{@link}">
                                        <xf:output value=".."/>
                                    </a>
                                </xf:group>
                                <xf:group ref=".[not(@link)]">
                                    <xf:output value="."/>
                                </xf:group>
                            </li>
                        </xf:repeat>
                    </ul>
                </xf:group>-->
            </xf:group>
        </div>
        <!-- Latest compiled and minified JavaScript -->
        <script type="text/javascript" src="https://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/2.2.2/jquery.min.js"></script>
        <script type="text/javascript" src="https://maxcdn.bootstrapcdn.com/bootstrap/3.3.6/js/bootstrap.min.js"></script>
    </body>
</html>
