<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../xsltforms/xsl/xsltforms.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xsltforms-options domengine="name=Fleur;url=../../xsltforms/js/fleur.js;uri=http://www.agencexml.com/Fleur;version=1.0"?>
<?xsltforms-options debug="no"?>
<?css-conversion no?>
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:cwb="http://bibfram.es/cwb/"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
    xmlns:ev="http://www.w3.org/2001/xml-events"
    xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/"
    xmlns:marc="http://www.loc.gov/MARC21/slim"
    xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#"
    xmlns:xf="http://www.w3.org/2002/xforms"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <head>
        <title>IVMOOC16 CoBRA Group 2 Project Website</title>
        <!-- Latest compiled and minified CSS -->
        <link rel="stylesheet"
            href="https://maxcdn.bootstrapcdn.com/bootstrap/3.3.6/css/bootstrap.min.css"/>
        <!-- Optional theme -->
        <link rel="stylesheet"
            href="https://maxcdn.bootstrapcdn.com/bootstrap/3.3.6/css/bootstrap-theme.min.css"/>
        <style type="text/css">
            <![CDATA[
            #wrapper{
                width: 80%;                
                min-height: 1000px;
                margin-top: 1%;
                margin-right: auto;
                margin-left: auto;
                margin-bottom: 2%;
                background-color: #C0C0C0;                
            }
            #title{
                text-align: center;
            }
            .xforms-label{
                
            }
            .checkbox{
                list-style-type: none;
            }
            #group-people{
                
            }
            #group-tasks{
               
            }
            #authorship{               
               width: 100%;
               margin-right: auto;
               margin-left: auto;
               text-align: center;
            }            
            .authors{
                margin-top: 1%;
                width: 20%;
                float: left;                                               
            }
            hr{
                color: white;
                width: 100%;
                float: left;
            }
            #sketches{
                width: 100%;
                margin-left: auto;
                margin-right: auto;
                
                
            }
            #choro{
                margin: 0 2% 0 0;
                width: 600px;
                float: left;
                                
            }
            #network{
                margin: 0 2% 0 0;
                width: 600px;
                float: left;
                
                                
            }
            #related-work{
                width: 100%;
                float: left;
            }
            #stats{
                width: 100%;
                float: left;
            }
            #viz{
                width: 100%;
                float: left;
            }
            #insights{
                width: 100%;
                float: left;
            }
            #if{
                width: 60%;
                height: auto;
            }
            #ls{
                width: 60%;
                height: auto;
            }
            #li{
                width: 60%;
                height: auto;
            }
            #sg{
                width: 100%;
                height: auto;
            }
            #f2m{
                width: 100%;
                height: auto;
            }            
            #gephi2{
                width: 100%;
                height: auto;
                background: black;
            }
            #citations{
                width: 100%;
                float: left;
            }
            .bold{
                font-weight: bold;
            }
            .ital{
                font-style: italic;
            }
            ]]>
        </style>
        <xf:model id="default-model">
            <xf:instance id="default-instance" src="data/data.xml"/>            
        </xf:model>
    </head>
    <body>
        <div id="wrapper" class="container">
            <div id="title">
                <h1>Comic Book Readership Archive (CoBRA)</h1>
                <h2>Exploring Comic Book Fan Mail across Gender and Geography</h2>
            </div>
            <xf:group ref="/data">
                <xf:group id="authorship">
                    <xf:repeat nodeset="group/people/person">
                        <div class="authors">
                            <a href="{@canvas}">
                                <xf:output value="name"/>
                            </a>
                            <div>Indiana University</div>
                            <xf:output value="@mail"/>
                        </div>
                    </xf:repeat>
                    
                </xf:group>                          
                <hr/>
                <xf:group id="scope">
                    <h3>Project scope and significance</h3>
                    <p>The project will produce a thematic visualization of published fan mail (taken from the time slice provided, 1961-1973) and consisting of several subcomponents that address the relevant themes in the dataset:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Geographic origin</li>
                        <li>Gender representation</li>
                        <li>Comic book series popularity</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>These subcomponent visualizations will provide a unified view of comic book readership in the form of a world geospatial representation with a count analysis of letters published and a network analysis of letter writers and comic book series. The discrete quantifiable measures will include letter-writer breakdowns from U.S. states and countries and correlations among gender, location, and comic book series.</p>                                                                                <p>The significance of the CoBRA project lies in its examination of an area of popular cultural studies--comic book fan letters--that has not yet been adequately research or documented. A historical database of fan letters provides a unique resource for answering research questions about the feedback loop between production and consumption in the comic book genre.</p>
                </xf:group>                
                <xf:group id="sketches">
                    <h3>Sketches/preliminary visualizations</h3>
                    <div id="choro">
                        <h4>Choropleth map of letters by U.S. state:</h4>
                        <img src="resources/letters-choro.svg" alt="Choropleth map of comic book fan letters by U.S. state" />    
                    </div>              
                    <div id="network">
                        <h4>Sample network visualization of comic book series and letter writers:</h4>
                        <img src="resources/cobra-network.svg" alt="Choropleth map of comic book fan letters by U.S. state" />
                    </div>
                </xf:group>
                <xf:group id="related-work">
                    <h3>Related work</h3>
                    <p>The textbook Visual Insights<sup>1</sup> contains exemplary visualizations and thematic presentations that are relevant to the CoBRA dataset, including the case studies "One Hundred Years of ISIS" (p. 262) and Visualizing NYC Hive (p. 268). The rough outline of our proposed CoBRA visualization is based on observing these thematic approaches to visualization and data encapsulation.</p>
                    <p>A search on some of the reference suggestions in the CoBRA project description reveals a few scholarly articles and materials relevant to the history of comic book readership and relevant to the formation of the CoBRA project. These references are useful for understanding the context around the project, but not in terms of auxiliary raw data or exemplary visualizations.</p>
                    <p>A search on comic-book readership online produces some more specific and contextually relevant data and visualization examples, including breakdowns of demographic-based and gender-based fan discussion and readership statistics. The Internet and Internet discussion and fan sites appear to be the modern replacement of older fan publications, and is naturally more expedient and simpler to harvest data from contemporary online sites and archives than from print sources. As an example, the Graphic Policy website details such statistics, as harvested from Facebook.<sup>2</sup>  depicts pie-charts and line graphs depicting comic book demographics).</p>
                    <p>Although interesting, it is not clear that online sites with present-day statistics provide any significant guidance to the task of characterizing, analyzing, and visualizing the historical data segment presented in the CoBRA project. An expanded scope that includes comparison to present-day statistics might be useful.</p>
                    <p>A previous version of the CoBRA dataset has been visualized by Anirudh R. A., Ashish Shendure, Brittany Yoder, Jae Eun Kum, and Shambhavi Dhargalkar.<sup>3</sup> Our work will differ from theirs by focusing more on geospatial and network visualization techniques. Another exemplary visualization cited by Anirudh R. A. et al., which includes digital images and transcripts of comic book fan letters, can be found on the hosted TimeMapper website.<sup>4</sup></p>                              
                </xf:group>
                <xf:group id="stats">                    
                    <h3>Data cleaning and preprocessing</h3>                                                       
                    <h4>Gender data</h4>                            
                    <p>The approach to gender identification of names was based on using the Social Security Tables from 1880-1914 to identify registration trends. The tables were globbed into a master table and sorted by occurrence based on gender. The dominant count was used as the basis of projection: for example, in the case of the name "Billy," the ambigendrous ratio is given by: <code>Billy</code><code>Male</code><code>381527</code> | <code>Billy</code><code>Female</code><code>5346</code>.</p> 
                    <p>Based on historic registrations, "Billy" was projected to be female in only 1.38% of occurrences. Therefore the code was designed to project the name as male (barring any obvious contraindications such as a <code>person_title</code> value of "Mrs."</p>
                    <h4>Geocoding data</h4>
                    <p>Geocoding data from the Google Map web services has been harvested and will be utilized in the project's next phase of visualizations. Using street-level geocoding from Google allows for more granular mapping and visualization versus centroid-based geocoding found in applications such as Tableau (also, Tableau allows for custom geocoding import, so one can gain very granular geocoding information and still use Tableau visualizations). The particular tools used included the geopy module and Python (registration with Google was necessary). A further advantage of Google is the byproduct of corrected, standardized addressing (i.e., address cleaning) for possible future incorporation into the dataset.</p> 
                    <p>In some cases preliminary cleaning of address data was necessary (e.g., where the city and state were recognizable but the country was left null). This process preceded more granular address cleanup.</p>                  
                    <h3>Summary statistics</h3>
                    <p>A summary of the dataset is presented in the table below. An initial count of names in the dataset yielded a total of 3,168 unique names. Person data is in the process of being further cleaned and reconciled, so this figure may change.</p>
                    
                    <table class="table table-striped">                       
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <td>Comic book series</td>
                                <td>Comic book issues</td>
                                <td>Fan letters</td>
                                <td>Countries</td>
                                <td>Unique names of letter writers</td>
                                <td>Gender of letter writers (inferred)</td>
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td>11</td>
                                <td>610</td>
                                <td>3703</td>
                                <td>38</td>                                
                                <td>3237</td>
                                <td>
                                    <table class="table table-striped">
                                        <thead>
                                            <tr>
                                                <td>Male</td>
                                                <td>Female</td>
                                                <td>Null</td>
                                            </tr>
                                        </thead>
                                        <tbody>
                                            <tr>
                                                <td>2863</td>
                                                <td>266</td>
                                                <td>108</td>
                                            </tr>
                                        </tbody>
                                    </table>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </xf:group>
                <xf:group id="viz">
                    <h3>Visualizations</h3>
                    <p>Our initial approach to visualizing the CoBRA data has focused on the variables of gender and geographic location (currently limited to US states). Methodologically, we have explored three techniques: statistical visualization, geospatial visualization, and network visualization.</p>
                    <h4><span class="bold">Statistical</span></h4>
                    <p>To analyze the fan letter data, a Pivot Table was created in Excel of all of the CoBRA data. For rows, the <code>series_name</code> and <code>issue_id</code> data fields were selected. For the value field, the count of <code>issue_id</code> was selected. This provided a count of fan letters for each individual issue and also provided an overall count of fan letters for each series.</p>
                    <p>To create a frequency distribution of fan letters and issues, columns were numbered from the lowest value of fan letters per issue (1) to the highest value (71). A binary <code>=if()</code> statement matrix was created, referencing the values in the pivot tables to those of the numbered columns. If the number of fan letters was equal to the column number, the cell would show 1. If it did not, the cell would show 0. The columns were then totaled to obtain the number of individual issues receiving each number of fan letters. Once these values were obtained, a scatterplot was created with the x-axis representing the number of fan letters and the y-axis representing the number of issues.</p>
                    <p>Referencing the same pivot table, a histogram of the total number of fan letters for each comic book series was created, as well as one for the average number of fan letters per issue in each series.</p>       
                    <p>An additional histogram was created to represent the breakdown of gender by state.</p>
                    <h5><span class="bold">Frequency distribution of fan letters and issues</span></h5>                    
                    <img id="if" src="resources/issue-freq.png" alt="Scatterplot of frequency distribution of fan letters and issues"/>
                    <hr/>
                    <h5><span class="bold">Total fan letters by series</span></h5>
                    <img id="ls" src="resources/letters-series.png" alt="Histogram of total fan letters by series"/>
                    <hr/>
                    <h5><span class="bold">Average number of fan letters per issue, grouped by series</span></h5>
                    <img id="li" src="resources/letters-issue.png" alt="Histogram of average number of fan letters per issue, grouped by series"/>
                    <hr/>
                    <h5><span class="bold">Bar graph of gender totals by state</span></h5>                    
                    <img id="sg" src="resources/state-gender.png" alt="Bar graph of gender totals by state"/>
                    <hr/>
                    <h4><span class="bold">Geospatial</span>: choropleth map of the proporation of female-to-male letter writers by US state</h4>
                    <p>To visualize the female-to-male proportion of CoBRA letter writers, R was utilized to analyze, clean, and reshape data.<sup>5</sup> From there, shape files from ArcGIS were used to map the female-to-male proportion of US letter writers. The data was read from R and persons were filtered by <code>id_person_dim</code> to identify unique authors and then grouped by gender and state to aggregate gender totals.</p> 
                    <p>The female-to-male proportion was calculated from these totals and map tools were used to map, fortify, and merge state dimensions to state names from the data file. This data was plotted as a Choropleth Map with ggplot2. The higher the proportion of female-to-male values, the darker the shade of red.</p>                       
                    
                    <img id="f2m" src="resources/f2m.png" alt="Choropleth map showing proportion of female-to-male letter writers by state"></img>
                    <hr/>
                    <h4><span class="bold">Network</span>: force-directed graph of comic book series and letter writers, color-coded by gender</h4>
                    <p>To visualize the connections among letter writers and comic book series, a force-directed network graph was encoded as a GraphML/XML file and rendered in Gephi. The BaseX XML database and XQuery interpreter was used to convert the CoBRA CSV data file into an internal XML representation. An XQuery script was then written to produce node and edge lists using GraphML notation. Node values were color-coded to distinguish between series nodes and letter-writer nodes, the latter of which were color-coded by gender (male, female, null).</p>
                    <p>The resulting GraphML file contained a total of 3248 nodes and 3482 edges. Once imported into Gephi, a series of network statistics was calculated, including degree, betweenness centrality, and modularity class. These statistics are still being explored and have not yet been incorporated into additional visualizations. The network was laid out using Gephi's implementation of the Fruchterman Reingold force-directed layout, with the following parameters:</p>
                    <table class="table table-striped">                       
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <td>Area</td>
                                <td>Gravity</td>
                                <td>Speed</td>                                
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td>10000.0</td>
                                <td>7.0</td>
                                <td>10.0</td>                                
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <p>Nodes were then sized by degree, on a scale of 8 to 50, and proportionally sized node labels were added. Labels were then filtered to show only those labels whose nodes had a degree greater than 9.</p>
                    <img id="gephi2" src="resources/cobra_gephi2.svg" alt="Force-directed network graph of comic book series with nodes color-coded by gender"/>
                    
                    
                </xf:group>
                <xf:group id="insights">
                    <h3>Insights</h3>
                    <p>The preliminary phase of visualization and analysis has revealed some basic insights regarding the contours of the data:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li><span class="ital">Fantastic Four</span> (901 issues) and <span class="ital">The Amazing Spider-Man</span> (1092 issues) represented the greatest portion of the data by series, but <span class="ital">The Avengers</span> and <span class="ital">The X-Men</span> had the highest average of number of letters per issue (8.28 and 7.69 letters per issue, respectively).</li>
                        <li>All 50 fifty US states and several other countries were represented in the data; California and New York were by far the biggest contributors.</li>
                        <li>The letter writers in the dataset were overwhelmingly male, but the most active letter writer (Shirley Gorman, with 17 letters) was female.</li>
                        <li>Alaska, New Hampshire, Idaho, Arizona, and New Mexico were the only states with a proportion of female-to-male letter writers greater than 25% (1:4).</li>
                        <li>By region, the Pacific Northwest had the highest proportion of female-to-male letter writers.</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>The next phase of visualization and analysis should yield additional insights into the connections among the people, places, and comic books represented in the dataset.</p>
                </xf:group>
                <xf:group id="citations">
                    <h3>Citations</h3>
                   
                        <p><sup>1 </sup>Börner, K., and D. E. Polley. 2014. <i>Visual Insights</i>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</p>
                        <p><sup>2 </sup><a href="http://graphicpolicy.com/2015/09/01/demo-graphics-comic-fandom-on-facebook-14/">http://graphicpolicy.com/2015/09/01/demo-graphics-comic-fandom-on-facebook-14/</a></p>
                        <p><sup>3 </sup><a href="http://ashishshendure.com/projects/ivmooc_cobra_2015/">http://ashishshendure.com/projects/ivmooc_cobra_2015/</a></p>
                        <p><sup>4 </sup><a href="http://timemapper.okfnlabs.org/anon/ik4x3a-timemapper-comics-readership-example">http://timemapper.okfnlabs.org/anon/ik4x3a-timemapper-comics-readership-example</a></p>
                        <p><sup>5 </sup>The following R packages were used: RCurl, dplyr, reshape2, ggplot2, map tools, scales, and RColorBrewer.</p>
                    
                </xf:group>
                
               <!-- <xf:group id="group-people" ref="group/people">
                    <h3>Group members: </h3>
                    <xf:repeat nodeset="person">
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                <a href="{name/@canvas}">
                                    <xf:output value="name"/>
                                </a>
                                <ul>
                                    <li>Roles: 
                                        <ul>
                                            <xf:repeat nodeset="roles/role">
                                                <li>
                                                    <xf:output value="."/>
                                                </li>
                                            </xf:repeat>
                                        </ul>
                                    </li>
                                </ul>
                                <ul>
                                    <li>Skills: 
                                        <ul>
                                            <xf:repeat nodeset="skills/skill">
                                                <li>
                                                    <xf:output value="."/>
                                                </li>
                                            </xf:repeat>
                                        </ul>
                                    </li>
                                </ul>
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </xf:repeat>
                </xf:group>-->
                <!--<xf:group id="group-tasks" ref="tasks">
                    <h3>Group tasks: </h3>
                    <ul>
                        <xf:repeat nodeset="task">
                            <li class="checkbox">
                                <xf:input ref="@completed">
                                    <xf:label/>
                                </xf:input>
                                <xf:output
                                    value="concat(substring(@date, 6, 2),
                                    '/',
                                    substring(@date, 9, 2),
                                    '/',
                                    substring(@date, 1, 4))"/>
                                <span>: </span>
                                <xf:group ref="@link">
                                    <a href="{@link}">
                                        <xf:output value=".."/>
                                    </a>
                                </xf:group>
                                <xf:group ref=".[not(@link)]">
                                    <xf:output value="."/>
                                </xf:group>
                            </li>
                        </xf:repeat>
                    </ul>
                </xf:group>-->
            </xf:group>
        </div>
        <!-- Latest compiled and minified JavaScript -->
        <script type="text/javascript" src="https://ajax.googleapis.com/ajax/libs/jquery/2.2.2/jquery.min.js"></script>
        <script type="text/javascript" src="https://maxcdn.bootstrapcdn.com/bootstrap/3.3.6/js/bootstrap.min.js"></script>
    </body>
</html>
